Okay, that's
I feel like doing some of the book,
okay?
We didn't do for a while.
Uh
So,
Nyak gyat D E N G space S A N G.
Uh try D E N G S A N G space N Y A N.
And you're not on the you're not on the
screen.
I don't see it.
Say again.
Uh
That's it.
All right, here we go.
Uh
we're just going to do the book for a
while.
Then we'll finish the meditations and
then I'll give you a dessert.
Which is a special sutra
that you can use during the retreat.
Okay.
Uh so, I have to watch the time.
4:44
pressure Okay.
Teng song nyen to she nyen pe tshe yo
gyang. So, most of you know there are
three
tracks.
The five there are five paths, right?
Spiritual evolution. Everybody
everywhere
goes through those five. Maybe this
life, maybe a thousand lives from now.
Everybody goes through those five.
Uh but you can do it on three different
levels of motivation or understanding,
okay?
The lowest one is called
listeners
which if you're studying Buddhism,
listener can also mean any disciple. So,
it's a dangerous word, okay? Second
track is called
self-made Buddhas lower case B
because they're not Buddhas. They're
just cool people, okay?
Third track
Bodhisattva, okay?
And the Bodhisattva track, those guys
are trying to save the world, okay?
Don't you know Bodhicitta, mind of
enlightenment, blah blah blah. Just
forget all that stuff.
Uh they want to save the world. They
want the whole world to be happy. That
that's what they want and they won't
take less, okay? That's a Bodhisattva.
So
here Pabongka Rinpoche says teng song
nowadays nyen to she nyen pe tshe de che
gyang. When we say he's just a listener
or she is just listener track, it sounds
like it's lower, okay?
But gyang de nyen den song nyen do do do
cha pe tshe de jo gyur. But if you had
the qualities that we just described
right? For the path of accumulation
you can see this is a real siddhi. This
is a real
high yogi, okay? Who who's on the lowest
track.
Someone who just had their first big
disaster in their life and they decide
to try Buddhism, they're already
very high in the universe, okay? Got it?
You can say high yogi, you're high
siddhi, okay?
Uh rang gyani cha pe gyat tsog sag pa so
nyen to le nyen den gyag gyur.
tong gyur And self-made Buddhas are a
thousand times cooler than that.
Okay? They're even more special, okay?
Uh
And they collect good karma for hundreds
of eons. Eon means
many millions of years, okay? To get to
the second track.
All right.
Chang chub sem pe yo nyen ne tam me pe
do wo yin te.
And the amount of karma that a
Bodhisattva is making is is can't
measure it compared to the first two,
okay?
Uh sog chog kyi nyen gyag sum pe tshe pe
sa la tong nyig den te sum gom la den na
pa. Here's an answer to a question that
some people had. He says
on the first two paths
called
accumulation and preparation before you
see emptiness directly, okay?
On those two pa- paths which in
technical Buddhism are called nyen pe
tshe pe sa. Nyen pe tshe pe sa means
uh they're just going on approximate
understanding,
okay? They're called nyen pe tshe pe sa.
It means
they're just dealing with approximate
understanding of what?
Emptiness, okay?
Uh
tong nyig den te sum gom pe den na pa.
They're trying to understand the pen.
They're struggling to understand the
pen. First two paths, okay? They just
got a
they came to their first DCI talk. This
strange guy
which might be Nick or Nick taught 550
600 people in
we split the DCI team last tour. It was
really cool. We covered 7,000 people in
two weeks
because we split the team
to different cities. So,
it might be the strange guy is Nick
standing up there with the pen.
And uh
the the audience when they first start
thinking about the pen and if they had a
personal disaster in their life, they're
already like
path of accumulation, okay? But their
understanding of emptiness is only
approximate and it's achieved through
conceptual means like trying to
understand
pictures in their mind. You know, I
think what he means is this, okay? It's
not correct. It's not exact. It's just
kind of rough
rough idea. Nyen pe tshe pe sa, okay?
But den na pa means they're getting
there.
They're making progress, okay?
They came to a lot of DCI talks.
How do you know someone came to a lot of
DCI talks?
When Geshe Michael pulls out the pen,
they
they're like, I can take a 5-minute nap.
Okay.
Just kidding.
Okay. Nyen je chang sem so me do wo nam
gyam pe sung chen do pa nyen gyi nyam me
pe tshe de tam me pe den pe tsog so.
Uh they are working on the idea of
compassion and helping all beings
and
a correct understanding of emptiness.
Uh
And they are
working on
the idea of getting rid of in tantra,
it's called the two vines.
The two
tree vines, okay? What's that mean?
On your central channel
here
goes like this
is uh two side channels, right? And they
represent
in in higher teaching, they represent
misunderstand people and misunderstand
things, okay?
Uh then at this point
uh the they're studying Bodhicitta,
they're studying higher teachings,
they're getting to understand the two
vines, okay?
Tok gyon nam me pe tshe de chang me do
wo tsog so. When you get to that stage
like close to the end of the second
path
it takes
chang me do wo. Say chang me.
do wo
What's chang me mean?
Where's my human dictionary?
He's not here. Oh, yeah.
Chang me means countless, okay? Tsog
means make
what do you call? Pile up karma. Pile up
karma. There are three stages in
becoming a Buddha. It's called the three
piling up karmas,
okay? But they're called the three chang
me piling up karmas, okay?
Which means
countless eons
piling up good karma, okay?
And and if you understand Abhidharma or
you can read Stanley's translation
it's like 1% finished.
Uh
It's a
It's a number. It's a name of a number.
It's Countless is not countless.
When you're talking about the three
pile up good karma to become a Buddha,
it it When you say it's countless, it's
a specific number of eons.
What is it? 10 to
the 60th power.
10 with 60 zeros after it. It's a
Buddhist number.
In Buddhism, each 10 has a different
name.
Okay? Each multiple of 10. So, take 10,
add 60 zeros,
that many of periods of millions of
years each, okay?
Is the the first stage.
Here, he says equal to the first two
paths.
Okay? How long does it take you to hear
the pen?
I don't know.
10 times 10 with 60 zeros times millions
of years times 1 and 1/2.
Okay? That's how long it took you
to get your first teaching on the pen.
Honestly, okay? According to him.
Okay?
Don't think it's easy to hear the pen.
The pen can put you to sleep, but it
took you a long time to get there.
Okay?
According to that, it took him many
millions of years
to get to the pen. You were a dog, you
were a fish, you were a bug, you were a
roach, not this roach.
Okay?
And after many many millions of years,
you became a human. And after many more
millions of years, you got to hear the
pen, okay?
Got it?
First
first of the three piles of good karma,
okay?
Then you have your experience of the
first direct perception of emptiness,
okay? And at the same period, you
perfect
the first perfection to an extraordinary
level.
First perfection?
Giving. Generosity, sharing what you
have, okay?
So, that's the first Bodhisattva level,
okay?
And it comes at the same time that you
see emptiness directly on a Bodhisattva
track, okay?
And then during the fourth path, which
is
path of
getting used to what you saw, okay?
During that time,
you perfect
How many perfections are left after
giving?
Trick question.
If you keep saying numbers, you'll hit
it.
There's a joke. They say if a
if a monkey hits a typewriter, then
after a while, they'll type some words,
you know?
Nine more.
10 10 Bodhisattva 10 perfections, right?
What are they? Number one?
Giving. Number two?
Morality, ethics. Number three?
No more anger. Number four?
Enjoy hard work.
Number five?
Meditation. Number six?
Yeah.
Then there's four more. These are called
the four ways of collecting disciples.
If you did DCI level eight, you know
them.
What's the first one? Doing nop shih.
Yeah, bribe them.
Offer them churros, ponchiks, or yochos.
Say, "Do you want to come to my class?"
They say, "No." You say, "There's free
refreshments." "Oh, yeah,
I'll come." Okay? Like help them
financially.
Make, you know, make it nice. Play rock
and roll during the class, stuff like
that, okay?
Second one?
What?
Yeah, encourage them, okay? Of course,
they don't do anything right, but if
they start to do something close, tell
them, "Oh, that's
you're really making progress."
If you're Connie, you're like, "Oh,
you're very close to enlightenment now."
Almost there.
You know,
you encourage them, okay?
Encourage
when your students do something right.
And as you know, if you're a parent,
it works better than criticizing, okay?
They do nine things wrong for every one
thing they do right.
But
you know, praise them for what they do
right. It works better.
Don't tell them nine bad things, okay?
What's number three?
Huh?
Yeah, try them try to get them I mean,
after you teach them, say, "Okay, now,
I taught you, you know, at the end of
this hour,
we're going to finish 27 meditations. Do
you promise to do at least one of them
during the next 3 days?"
Okay? Like try to get them to make a
commitment
to actually try it themselves, okay?
It's not enough to teach.
And that's again why I like the
Singapore group, you know? They are
and Guangzhou also, very strong. Jasmine
and
Yeah.
Vivian, they are
they are trying to get the students to
do it, you know? So, don't just teach
them and go away for a year.
Who does that?
Uh
Like teach them and then, you know, have
follow-up. Make sure they're doing it,
okay? Reach out each other.
Tell them what you're doing, okay?
All right, last one?
Yeah, last one is In English, there's an
idiom called practice what you preach or
walk the talk.
And it means
be a good example, you know? It it
doesn't help to
describe
how cool it is if you're not doing it
yourself. And what's the famous example
of in DCI?
No, I went to see one of my students
teach meditation. I sat in the back.
And
they they were going to say they said,
"I'm going to teach meditation." Then
then they would reach for the cup, you
know? And they're like this.
Then I There were two ladies sitting
close to me, and one of them said to the
other lady,
"I don't know what kind of meditation
she's teaching, but I don't want to
learn it."
Okay?
Okay? Got it?
So, you have to be the
do it yourself, right? Those are the 10
perfections, okay? Six usual
perfections.
Where do you go for four more
on top, okay?
Uh Now, I'm
Young Chen Seng So Dong Bo E Lu Geda.
Now, he's going to start something
called
the 12
sets of 100 each. The 12 sets
of 100 each. He's still talking about
how cool is Sangha Jewel. He's still
talking about how cool is Sangha Jewel,
okay?
And he says,
"Even a Bodhisattva at level one, first
level Bodhisattva, just saw emptiness
directly, wants to help the whole world,
okay?" That's what a first level
Bodhisattva is, okay?
Even they have the 12
kinds of 100 each, okay? So, here you
go. Here they are.
Number one,
uh
they have the power to send out 100
bodies at a time
to help people. Already, they have
power.
Okay? First level Bodhisattva.
Number one. Number two.
Uh Each of the bodies they send out has
100 Bodhisattvas
sitting around it.
Okay?
They can send out 100 bodies.
Each body they send out has 100 more
bodies
sitting around it, okay?
Uh that's a good question. It just says
Bodhisattva.
You can be a Bodhisattva without being
an Arya if you're on the Bodhisattva
track and all you did was first two
paths and you did not travel lower path
previously.
If if you're interested,
uh number three,
they can see 100
eons ahead.
Okay? Number four,
when they see emptiness directly,
100 planets
shake.
Okay?
In Buddhism, we say if something really
cool happens, the earth can't
hold the karma up, and then earth will
go like this.
Okay? Where did we have a nice
earthquake? Uh
Was it LA?
Yeah, it's kind of scary.
And in China, I think we had one.
Anyway, we did it a few times.
I remember in Taiwan we made it snow
when it never snowed before. Okay.
Uh
Number five, ting nge zin gyi go gyad
tal la jupa. They can
go into a hundred different kinds of
meditation.
Okay.
Uh
Number six, right?
They see a hundred Buddhas.
Number seven, those hundred Buddhas each
one gives them blessing.
Number eight, uh
they can emanate a hundred Buddha
paradises.
Number nine, they can go to those
hundred paradises.
Number 10,
uh
they can make a hundred distinctions
between subtle
kinds of phenomena. Okay, like a hundred
distinctions about emptiness, okay?
And teaching about it. Sem chen gyam
meen pa, they can
help
ripen a hundred living beings.
Okay?
In this case, ripen means I'm sorry, in
this case hundred just means
zillions, okay?
Lots.
Many.
Okay. Uh
number what?
Uh 11, right?
That was 11.
We okay?
Let's do nine is they can go to a
hundred Buddha paradises.
Eight is they can create a hundred
Buddha paradises.
Got the difference?
10 is they can
teach a hundred teachings about a
hundred kinds of emptiness, like that.
Number 11,
they can ripen hundred living beings,
but it means many hundred.
And number 12,
uh
kalpa gyane pa,
they can stay for a hundred eons.
Okay. Now, my
my opinion, okay? This is my opinion. I
think this list is exaggerated.
Okay. In some ways it's exaggerated, in
some ways it's not cool enough.
Okay. I I don't believe, for example,
that uh
that someone who just reached
the direct procession of emptiness on
Bodhisattva track can emanate a a
hundred Buddha paradises. I don't think
so. Okay, to be honest.
I think this is some kind of uh
slightly exaggerated tradition to get
people excited.
Okay? And I've told you before what does
happen.
Okay? You see you're going to be a
Buddha. You see that Buddha. You meet a
Buddha.
Uh
you you have an experience of
bodhicitta. You can read the minds of
every living being. You can see their
face.
Those are bigger, right? Than this.
So, this list is I in my opinion,
uh it's just a little bit some of it's a
little bit exaggerated and some of it's
not enough.
Okay.
But, I have to teach it to you cuz it's
in the book. Okay.
Ta chen du uh chu nyi pa red ne ja drol
we sa nyi pa tong tak.
Then, that's at first Bodhisattva level.
At the second Bodhisattva level,
multiply these numbers times a thousand.
Okay?
At the third Bodhisattva level, multiply
each number by a hundred thousand.
At the fourth Bodhisattva level,
multiply each number by a billion.
I put the numbers there for you, okay?
Cuz they're kind of complicated.
At the fifth Bodhisattva level, multiply
by 10 billion.
At the sixth Bodhisattva level, multiply
by one quadrillion.
12 zeros, right?
Something like that.
Uh at the seventh Bodhisattva level,
multiply times 10 to the 14th power.
At the eighth Bodhisattva level,
multiply by a hundred sis
a hundred thousand times
the pieces of dust in a million planets.
Okay?
Uh on the ninth Bodhisattva level,
uh the dust of 10 to the 67th power,
okay?
And then at the tenth Bodhisattva level,
forget it. There's no description.
Okay.
He says uh indescribable number of
galaxies full of dust.
Okay.
Dor na,
uh
briefly,
ma da sa dung gyi kapa ta meen nyi pa.
Okay?
At the
first
Bodhisattva level,
sorry.
At the first two paths,
they completed the first collection of
karma.
And it took
10 times six 10 to the 60th zeros
eons.
Okay?
Now, to get from there
to get from the pen
to the seventh Bodhi Sa- seventh
Bodhisattva level, takes another 10 to
the 60th power.
Uh that's how long our Buddha took,
okay?
And then uh to cover Bodhisattva levels
eight, nine, 10,
uh
takes another 10 to the 60th power,
okay? But,
if you study Tsongkhapa lineage,
if you
just
relax and learn these ideas like we
teach them in DCI,
uh you can finish in about 500 years.
And it sounds like a long time, but it's
not.
Uh
Life goes on pretty fast, you know? I
can tell you.
I was 20 yesterday.
It just went boom, you know? You're
like, "Whoa, wait.
Slow down."
So, don't worry about it. Seven
lifetimes.
Okay? Not much.
Okay? It's really not very much. It goes
very fast.
Okay. Uh mi shin gyi ge cha me tsom me
ta gen nyi gyi nyen che me pa yin tso.
Anyway,
the
Sangha jewel is cool.
Okay? That's all he wanted to say.
That's all That's all he wanted to say.
Sangha jewel is cool. Okay?
Uh I'm going to do the sutra with you
because we don't have time to do much
more of the book.
There's a
later in a in a few pages,
he's going to mention uh
called Buddha anusmriti. Say Buddha.
Buddha anu anu smriti smriti Buddha
Buddha anu anu smriti smriti It's a
sutra.
Okay? It's a
It's a short sutra, okay?
It's only a few pages long, okay?
And it's called uh
It's called how to think about the
Buddha, you know?
Like if you have time sometimes
and you're just, you know, having a hot
cocoa and you're sitting in your porch
in the afternoon at home on Sunday,
you don't have to work,
you can read this sutra. It's good luck.
Okay? I translated it this morning.
Yesterday morning. It's a short sutra,
okay? And uh
It's so important
that every time the monks and nuns do
their confession, we have to read it
together, okay?
So, if you're a monk or nun, you have to
say this one every two weeks.
Okay?
Uh so, it's very important for
cleaning karma, also.
Bad karma, okay?
Did we translate it, Stanley?
That seems contradiction.
It has to be cleaned up, okay? You'll
get it after the retreat, okay?
I'm sorry we couldn't finish it, but uh
Here's the English, okay?
I'm going to just
teach it to you and explain it to you,
okay?
And I found a commentary.
I found two commentaries,
okay? So, I'm going to teach you from a
commentary.
Cuz some parts are difficult, okay?
And I'll I'll just read it to you for
good luck. It's called lung, okay? And
uh
So, this is the first English lung, I
think.
Uh in the language of India, this book
is called Arya Buddha anusmriti.
In the language of Tibetan, it is called
Pakpa Sangye Jetsun Drolma. I don't know
in Chinese what
title.
Remembering the Thinking about the
Buddha.
Yeah, that's what I said. Okay.
In the English language, it is called
Exalted Lines on Thinking of the Buddha.
How do How do
How do relax on your porch on Sunday
afternoon
with a iced tea or coffee or okay?
And how to just
think cool things about Buddha. That's
all. That's the sutra, okay? It's
supposed to be done relaxed.
Go to a Starbucks Shambhala
and you know, have a coffee and just
read it to yourself, okay?
I bow down to all Buddhas and
Bodhisattvas.
And a Buddha, a conqueror, is the one
gone thus.
The enemy destroyer.
The totally enlightened one.
The one who possesses both knowledge and
the legs, okay? We'll talk about it.
He or she
is the one gone to bliss.
Knower of the world.
Matchless charioteer who tames all
beings.
Teacher of gods and men.
The Buddha, the conqueror.
And the ones thus gone come from a cause
of the same, from merit.
The star of their virtue will never go
by.
They are dressed in the jewels of
patience.
They are the earth with minds of men.
They are studded with the gems of the
sacred marks.
The flowers of their sacred signs are in
full bloom.
They come to us in a way that fits each
one of us.
And when we lay our eyes upon them,
nothing but harmony comes among us.
They please those with thoughts of
faith.
Nothing can outshine their wisdom.
Their strength can never be overpowered.
They are the teachers of all living
beings.
The fathers and mothers of the
Bodhisattvas.
Kings and queens of those who have seen
the void.
They captain the ship for those who
travel to the city of Nirvana.
Their knowledge is incalculable.
Their courage is inconceivable.
Their words are pure.
The song they sing is exquisite.
Uh I made a mistake here. We cannot get
enough of looking upon them, right?
Their holy form has no equal.
They cannot be stained by the realm of
desire.
form.
They can never be compromised by the
realm of the formless.
They are free of pain.
They are forever free of this mortal
coil.
I'm reading a slightly earlier
translation. Probably you have a few
changes. Uh
no longer do they possess the parts of a
human human being.
They have mastered the doors of sense.
They have sliced away all knots.
They are free of regrets.
They are free of craving.
They have crossed the great water.
Their wisdom is complete.
They live within the wisdom of Buddhas
gone and yet to come and here among us.
Never do they stay in Nirvana.
They dwell in the end of all things.
And they make their home in a place
from where they can watch over each one
of us.
These then are the magnificent qualities
of the immaculate wisdom
of the ones who've gone that way. That's
a whole sutra.
Okay?
Cool?
So sometimes during retreat now your
retreat getting very busy, I think.
Uh
You can If you get tired, okay? Like you
don't want to go for a walk.
I I don't like walks, okay?
I'm supposed to.
So I'll just sit on my on Gelse's porch
and
you know, drink a watermelon juice and
read the sutra and relax and listen to
the birds, okay?
All right.
So this is a very famous refuge
practice.
Just to read the sutra and think about
it.
I'm going to give you some notes for the
sutra, okay?
Uh these are from several different
lamas.
And it's kind of nice because he
explains
the meaning
of common synonyms for Buddha, like
Tathagata, Sugata,
okay? Ready?
Uh we call them
those who've gone that way. Is that one
of the first ones, I think.
Gone thus.
Okay.
Because
uh
Tashi Namgyal
Dongwa Tsongkhapa
Yeshe Drakpa.
Because they
have gone
to a place
where they will never again not be
meditating on emptiness directly.
Okay? So they are called gone thus.
Okay? They've They just went into a
meditation from which they will never
come out.
Called direct perception of emptiness. A
Buddha, okay?
So they went that way. Got it?
Thusness is
to you know, to ta.
Uh
Okay.
Uh Nyam mong de de pa da chomba na. He
doesn't cover all of them, okay? So tell
me which ones he doesn't cover, I'll
give them to you from another
commentary.
He says they are enemy destroyer
because they destroyed their own
negative emotions forever, okay?
Yen ten ma lu pa chin chi ma lu pa ton
nyam da pa tso pa.
Uh they are reach total enlightenment
because
they totally got all the good qualities.
Okay?
So we say total Buddha, right? Totally
enlightened Buddha.
Ma rig pa nyi sang shing
she ja la log pa na sang gye.
Now why are they called Buddha? Why are
they called Buddha?
Okay?
Buddha has
uh
two meanings, okay?
One meaning of bud, the Sanskrit root
bud is to wake up.
Okay?
Uh
And one is uh
the root vid,
which means what?
Vid video.
To see, okay? So b u d
is related to v i d in Sanskrit, okay?
So when you say the word Buddha,
the Tibetans did a very smart thing.
They said
sang
gye.
They used two different words glued
together.
Okay? The Tibetan word for Buddha
has is very smart because it includes
both meanings of bud.
Okay? Wake up and see all things, okay?
So
How did they wake up? They woke up from
the sleep of misunderstanding.
How did they spread? How did they grow?
How did they see?
Uh
their
mind has expanded to the vision of all
things, okay? So they are called
woke up
wide vision. How's that? Okay? Something
like woke wide. Woke wide?
Okay.
We call them woke wide.
Mm.
They are said to possess knowledge. Is
that the next one?
Okay. They possess knowledge
because they have the first of the three
Buddhist trainings. What's that?
Uh yeah, but he's going the other way.
Wisdom, okay? Understand emptiness,
okay?
That's therefore they have knowledge,
Then there's a strange part. If you
don't have a commentary, you're going to
get lost. It says they have
legs.
That doesn't seem like a big deal.
You know.
Oh, you got legs, so do I.
I'm not even a Buddha, I got legs.
Okay. My legs hurt. Okay.
Uh
It means they have the first two
trainings,
which is morality
and Concentration.
Yeah, concentration. Or you can say for
the concentration, you can also say
uh
Well, let's leave it at concentration.
Okay.
Why do they call those two legs?
They support the third. Yeah, they're
the support for the third one, which is
wisdom. Okay?
So, there's three Buddhist trainings. Uh
morality,
concentration, wisdom. You need the
first two to support the third one. So,
they're called legs. Oh, you got legs.
Thanks.
You mean I have good morality and good
contemplation. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Okay.
All right.
Uh
Why What's the next one?
Sugata?
Huh?
Yeah, the one gone to bliss, the one
gone to happiness. Sugata in Sanskrit.
Okay?
Uh
They reached
ultimate wisdom, and they got rid of all
their bad things, so they are gone to
bliss. Okay?
Next one.
They know the world.
Okay.
It means
uh
they can read their disciples'
minds and know what they need.
Okay, perfectly.
Okay? They see what seeds the student
has in their mind.
Uh
They see what's their capacity. They see
what's their What do you call that?
Proclivities.
Uh
The talents. Aptitude. Aptitude. They
can tell how much aptitude. Okay? And
they teach the right thing at the right
time for that person's mind. Okay?
All right. That's what it means to know
the world.
Uh
Why are they the charioteer?
Who what?
Tames all living beings. Okay?
In a you can say uh car driver. They are
your chauffeur.
Okay? They are the ultimate chauffeur.
Why?
Uh
They know the right road to take to
to
redirect people who are going the wrong
way.
Okay? So, when the student starts going
the wrong way,
the Buddha says turn right or turn left.
Okay?
And uh
And they put them on the best What do
you call?
The best GPS road to enlightenment. They
are the ultimate GPS.
Okay? Dharma GPS. That's what this one
means. Okay?
Uh
Uh what's the next one?
Yeah, teacher of gods and men. Jigme
says I should use humans, but I don't
know. I I just gods and men is an old
expression in English. Men doesn't mean
males. It means all human beings. Maybe
you can say gods and women.
Okay.
Uh
Then they know
how to teach people what to do and not
and what to not do. That's all. Okay?
They can teach people what to do and
what not to do.
Okay?
So, they are
They are What is it? Teacher of gods and
men. Okay?
Now, there's one irritating one. Sorry.
That
uh isn't clear to me.
And it was something about they come
from
a cause which is similar or something
like that.
Well, how do they say it go? Say it out
loud.
And the ones thus gone
from a cause of the same. Yeah, a cause
of the same. Okay? That one's not clear.
So, I found that in a commentary by
anybody somebody.
And they said
uh
What created those Buddhas is that they
tried to help many people earlier.
That's all. That's the meaning of that
one.
Okay? Anyone I didn't cover?
Anyone you want to know?
We okay? Huh?
Which one?
Oh, good. Let's look up that one. Okay.
Uh
here's how it was explained by Who is
this person?
Uh
my common
Uh somebody named Dzigar Rinpoche.
Uh
They destroyed all obstacles.
Okay?
That's how he said it.
And they destroyed the four demons.
Okay?
Four demons are I don't know, death, old
age,
Yeah, negative emotions and uh
the divine youth, which means
cruel things that distract you from
Dharma. Okay.
All right. Any more?
Anything we didn't cover?
Speak now or forever hold your own
peace.
We finished it.
Didn't we?
Yeah, we did.
Oh, same thing. Yeah. Okay.
Okay.
Conqueror.
Bhagavan. Bhagavan.
And that has That's a long story, but
that's how it's explained here. Okay, so
anyway,
if you want to think about Buddha jewel,
uh you can recite this out loud quietly
on your porch. Okay?
And praise the Buddha. All right?
And it's a very powerful practice. It's
a very powerful sutra. Okay?
All right. Let's finish the meditations,
and then we can go close your retreat
border,
and send WeChat
to rest for a few days.
Okay.
WeChat, take a few days off.
Number 25. Okay?
Meditation 25, page 11.
Now, the 10th
refuge vow
is that you're supposed to take refuge
three times every day and three times
every night. That's the 10th refuge vow.
We'll talk about it later.
But,
the good news is
if you understand
what taking refuge is,
especially if you understand that taking
refuge is deciding and not to tell your
husband how stupid he is,
it's easy to do it six times a day.
Okay?
Someone will irritate you
six times a day.
That's why we get married.
It's automatic.
In your own house.
You don't have to go anywhere.
Okay? Six times a day
your partner will upset you.
Okay? Big upset or little upset. I mean,
Michael Dunn never does, I know, but
uh
you can borrow somebody or something. I
don't know.
Uh anyway,
if you understand what refuge really
means,
this meditation says, "Can I remember
the pen six times a day?" Yes. Okay, no
problem. Okay?
Otherwise, if refuge means I have to go
to the temple and burn incense,
then six times a day is a problem. I
won't have time to do anything else.
Okay? It doesn't mean that.
It means understanding emptiness six
times a day. Okay?
And And I don't know.
If I drive from my house to Village of
Oak Creek,
six people will irritate me in traffic.
Then I'm like, "Thank you. Now I'm done
for the day."
You know? Jigme can drive me home.
Okay?
I can cover it in just that 25-minute
drive. I can do my six times refuge.
Seriously. Sometimes I forget and I just
get pissed off at them.
What is wrong with you? Why are you
driving?
Okay? Then if you just remember, "Oh,
that's coming from me."
Why do I have to see people breaking the
rules so often?
There's a joke in DCI. What's the joke?
I don't know why I have to see somebody
talking too much. Nick, what is that?
Nick's like
Okay.
There's a DCI joke, you know. I don't
know why I have to see people eating
sweets all day.
Okay.
Uh so 25 is just
You know,
there's you will get sunburned or some
bug will get into your bed and keep you
up for 2 hours and
you know, something will happen during
retreat. Don't worry.
Demons don't like people doing retreat.
They will come.
The minute you put up your What's the
marker?
It's a advertisement for demons.
Haunted this house.
Someone's trying to meditate.
All right.
That's the real meaning of this Om mani
padme hum.
Okay. Come, bother me.
And you know, something will happen.
Last time what happened, I remember
the handle came off of somebody's
bathtub and all the water for every
house is pushing out of the
one bathtub, you know. Me and Tim had a
Was it you and me?
We had a good time that night.
Geshe was the hero. Him and me were
watching.
We're like, "Oh my god, nobody will have
any water in about half an hour."
And okay, the minute you start doing
retreat, something will happen.
And
cuz they want you to spend the rest of
your life
looking at
cat videos on YouTube.
Okay?
They don't want you doing retreat.
Okay? They don't want you doing retreat.
The demons don't like it when people do
retreat.
And and very very serious things will
happen to people in retreat, okay? And
we proved it here.
Yeah, and it happens, okay? So when
stuff happens,
you should feel proud, you know.
You know, Penny, did you get any
obstacles? No, Geshe la, everything went
smooth. I got obstacles.
The demons thought I was going to do
something cool.
So they came to my cabin and they left
you alone.
You know, I attracted demons. I must
have been doing some good practice.
You didn't have any demons. Don't worry,
next time if you work hard, you can get
some demons.
Okay. All right.
Okay, so that's
Demons are good cuz it gives you a
chance to take refuge, okay? Then you
can keep your refuge vow. If the demons
come six times a day,
you should be happy. Yes, madam.
Yeah, number one, demons don't like it.
It's called go number. In Tibetan,
there's a special word.
If you stick your head up out of the poo
poo,
I'd like to get out.
They're looking to see if anyone
is not looking at cat videos all day.
You know, they're like, "I don't want to
look at cat videos." Boom. Go back to
the cat videos.
You know, they're When you stick your
head up, it's called go number. They
will
take you back down, okay? Why they don't
like it
is
bad deed number nine.
Because of our human tendency to be
unhappy when other people succeed. We
are so happy when a movie star Oh, Brad
Pitt divorced Angela And-
Angelina Jolie. Oh, really? Tell me. He
threw something at her. Oh, really? Now,
you can hear it like for 2 hours on uh
the lawyers are, you know, talking about
what he threw at her.
And
people Why is it on the radio? Why they
put it on the internet?
Cuz we like it. Oh, really? Tell me
more.
Did he hit her or just missed her?
You know, and okay, and that causes
demons. Yeah, the demons are coming from
us.
Because we're so interested about movie
stars' troubles.
Okay. All right. And and I am too. I
mean, it's it's almost un- What do you
call it?
It's it's part of us, you know. What was
that recently?
I don't know.
Anyway.
We loved Oh, the two guys got fired in
the government.
Yeah, one guy Oh, did you hear he was
talking to the Russians, but he said he
wasn't talking to the Russians and so
they fired him. Oh, really? Tell me
more, you know. And the other guy was
just mean all the time.
Anyway.
Oh, tell me more. Which one? What did he
say? Who fired him? You know, like that,
okay?
Uh
okay, number 26.
What time I have to finish?
4:45. Don't cheat me.
4:45. Okay.
Uh
Number 26 is
I will offer my day-to-day honesty and
integrity to the Buddhas.
This is one of the
refuge vows and I can't remember which
one. Is that Am I a bad person?
I'll have to go look it up.
It because the
I think it might be.
Let's see.
Yeah, it is.
Yeah.
So this refuge vow, which is to put all
your hopes
in objects of refuge every time you do
something.
Yeah, but Bokar Rinpoche says
it involves
offering your day-to-day honesty and
integrity to the Buddhas. Okay, now
that's not what you would expect, so I
made it a
a meditation, okay?
It it
it doesn't seem to equal
putting all your trust in the three
jewels, but somehow it is and maybe you
can meditate on it and figure it out and
tell me when you get out.
Okay.
Uh
So during this meditation number 26,
uh think of all the times you've been
honest.
Think of all the times you've been uh
honest person in the last few days, few
weeks.
And offer it
to the Buddhas and you are you are
taking refuge. You are fulfilling your
refuge vows, okay?
So that's a pleasant meditation, you
know. All the times I was honest in the
last few weeks, okay?
A lot of these are not like
confession where you have to think of
what a bad person you are. Of course you
are.
But
during these meditations,
you're supposed to be thinking all the
good things you're doing, okay? It's
like coffee meditation, okay?
Uh number 27.
And that's the final part of the
teaching on refuge in the Lamrim.
Okay, what happens next in Guadalajara?
We go to karma.
We start studying karma.
And the DCI people are going to be
excited
in Guadalajara
because then we go deep into the laws of
karma.
You know, the four laws of karma
and the four flowers.
And all that's going to come in
Guadalajara, okay? So
we'll be finished with refuge this week.
And then in Guadalajara in August? July.
We will do karma. Just karma, karma,
karma, okay? So if you really ever
wanted to know about karma,
come to that, okay?
Uh
It's a very
detailed uh teaching about karma, okay?
How does karma work?
Uh so the last last last
refuge meditation,
the last last last advice
in the Lamrim. By the way, this is
called Nong tri. Nong tri is as opposed
to pe tri. Pe tri means uh
teach the people the scripture. Nong tri
means
put them in retreat and let them
experience that Lamrim
level. You know, teach them meditations
that will help them to experience
refuge.
So we're doing both. We're doing pe tri.
I'm explaining the book to you. Then
you're going to go do a Nong tri or Nyam
tri.
You're going to go put the teaching into
personal experience, okay? And that's
another way to do Lamrim. If you do a
tough Lamrim
program, you teach people, you know, the
the eight Lamrim books
together. It's called
I'm sorry.
Well,
he used eight. Four is also traditional.
Four great books on Lamrim.
And that takes a long, long time.
And then you require that the student
reach that level before they can go on
to the next one.
You test them.
Are they taking refuge six times a day?
You test them. And if they're not, you
don't let them go to karma.
But it would be impractical cuz cuz
I'd have to do karma over like 100
times, you know.
Okay? It's for a lama who has a few good
students, okay? Like that.
All right.
So, number 27, the final refuge
teaching, which we will get to in the
book I I hope after the
three-day retreat.
It's he he says something very cool. He
says, "Look, either jump or don't jump."
Okay? Don't stand on a cliff.
You know?
Did you ever jump off one of those
cliffs
into the ocean?
I think I did it once. It's really
scary.
You know? And you say, "Oh, I can do
that, you know?" And then your friend
says, "Okay, let me see you do it." And
you go up to the edge and you look over
and you say, "I don't know.
Maybe I can't do it, you know?"
It doesn't hurt too much if you if you
land on your feet. He's going to land on
his head. That hurts.
But it doesn't hurt too much
if you don't hit a rock.
So,
he says, "Don't stand on the top and go,
'I don't know, you know?
This is I don't know if I want to do
this or not.' Don't In English, we say
don't be wishy-washy.
Don't say, "I don't know if I want to do
it or not, you know? Maybe I'll do it,
maybe I won't, you know?"
He says, "If you're going to take
refuge, jump.
Just jump, okay? Stop using science,
start using seeds, okay? Just jump,
okay?" And he says, "Don't
around."
Okay?
Like just jump,
the last refuge advice
is
go for it, man.
What the hell? Just jump.
You know? Start using seeds to run your
life.
You know? Stop thinking about doctors
and jobs and
you know?
Marriage counselors, just jump.
Start using seeds for everything.
Okay?
So,
maybe you can do that meditation on
Thursday morning.
Okay? Am I jumping or not? And just
jump, you know? By Thursday morning,
you're supposed to be like
the meditation is the calm of Diamond
Mountain retreat cabin
finally reached your mind.
And in that enlightened space, you
decide, "I'm changing from now on.
I'm going to jump.
No more
No more like I don't know, I don't know,
okay? From now on, seeds, seeds, seeds,
okay? For everything I want.
Okay? And jump. Okay? By Thursday
morning, I'm I
do this last, okay? Thursday morning
meditation.
Okay? What time is it?
Yeah, at 7:15.
At 7:45 on Thursday in the morning, do
this meditation.
At 7:45
on Thursday morning, which is your last
serious meditation
during the three days, do this one.
I'm going to jump or I'm not going to
jump. So, don't do it before that. Okay?
Save it for the end.
Cuz hopefully by that time the retreat
cottage had an effect on your mind.
And you will have more courage, you
know? I'm going to jump.
No more
self-existent aspirants, you know?
I'm jumping,
okay? I'm going for it, okay?
That should be your last meditation,
okay?
All right, then. Now,
don't forget you have this sweet death
meditation.
Okay? Oh, sorry, there's another one
before that. I'm sorry. There is a 28.
Oops.
Okay, two more meditations if you want.
By the way, nobody can do 28 meditations
in three days. It's it's
don't even try. Pick the ones that
you're attracted to, okay? Choose the
Have this book with you.
You can say, "That one I That sounds
boring.
That one's depressing.
This one looks pretty cool."
Okay? You choose.
Okay? You choose your meditations, all
right?
That's why I gave you 28 choices. It's
actually 29, okay?
Here's 28.
It has three steps, very famous Lamrim
taking refuge meditation. Number one,
decide I already went there.
Okay? I already went there. Where? Lower
realms. Lower realms.
I'm in hell.
I'm an animal.
I'm a hungry spirit. Decide you already
went there, okay?
What's the photograph?
This is a famous photo that was taken
during the Vietnam War.
And these people are being shot at right
right at that moment. Somebody's trying
to kill them right at that moment, okay?
It's like a hell.
They jump into the water.
They can't stay under the water. They
have to put their head up.
In that moment, someone was shoot a real
It's a real photo.
Someone was trying to kill them at that
moment, okay? And and this guy took a
photo.
And he survived. And uh
It's just a normal family. There's a mom
and there's the mom, her her daughter,
grandma, mom, and kids. And someone's
trying to kill them in this moment of
that photograph, okay?
Why we talking about that? Imagine
you're already in the hell realms. Like
you didn't take refuge very well. You
spent the three days on your cell phone.
So, you went to a place like that, okay?
Then your mind will object.
Your mind will say, "No, no, no, no. I'm
in Diamond Mountain in a nice,
comfortable, beautiful, cool retreat
cottage because of Melissa and Michael.
You know, I'm
and I'm here. I'm I'm I'm I'm not in the
hell. Nobody's shooting at me."
Okay?
Then step number two, what's that?
I do have the seeds.
Okay? If I died this afternoon, I would
go to a place like that, okay?
So, first part, I am in the hells
already.
Then your mind will say, "No, no, no.
No, no, no. I'm in a retreat cottage in
Diamond Mountain. It's hot as hell, but
it's not hell."
Then you
Then you have to look into your mind,
you know? Do you have the seeds or not?
And then the answer is yes, I have the
seeds. I could go there. If I died this
afternoon, you know? If I'm the first
person to die from Ronald McDonald
It's possible I could go there. And then
third
is supposed to be happy thought. What's
that?
I have shelter. Like a son,
a small boy
who's who has dad he can hang on to dad
and say, "Help me, Dad." Okay? Who Who's
that? Buddha, Dharma, Sangha, okay? I
have
I have shelter. I have refuge. I have
protection. I can hang on to my dad.
Okay? Like that, okay? All right?
Try to remember the photographs. Try to
memorize the photographs, okay?
You can give yourself a photo quiz.
Look at the photos and say, "What was I
supposed to meditate about?" Okay? And
and then you won't forget the
meditations. You can do them
after you get home. It's on the bus, on
the airplane, okay?
When your flight's delayed in the LA
airport.
Or you're in the LA customs line for two
hours.
Don't waste your time. Okay? Who was
that? Me and Nick did the whole
translator program design
waiting in a customs line
where?
Thailand?
Yeah.
Phuket, 11:00 at night.
Something like that.
I don't remember.
Okay, that's another meditation you can
do. Okay, now,
if you want to get to the first one
conveniently, what's the first one of
those three?
You're in the hell and somebody's
shooting at you, etc., okay?
Do the meditation after it first.
What's that?
Death meditation. Go through the stages
of death.
Okay? If it's If you have difficulty
jumping into being shot at,
do the death meditation before it.
Then you're reviewing the last part of
the lamrim before refuge.
You you're reviewing that one, which is
death meditation, okay? So, tie together
retreat number 22, retreat number 23,
retreat number 24, and retreat number
25, okay? Those of you who came to them,
who's smart enough to come to them,
uh tie them together. You know, try to
remember
what came before, and don't don't let it
go when you do the next lamrim, okay?
Don't
don't forget about death meditation when
you start refuge.
And when you reach karma in Guadalajara,
don't give up don't drop the refuge,
okay? Like try to
keep some continuity of the lamrim,
okay?
Da da da da da da da da da,
da da da da da da da da da da da da da.
I finished the meditation book, and you
didn't. Okay.
Uh
Okay?
I can take one question.
I think I promised two people.
Quick.
How do you say mhm?
Mhm
I promised two people, right?
Like this.
So,
uh
We have learned to take refuge even in
the moment when somebody shoots a gun at
us.
Yeah.
I have a feel much more simple problem.
This translation tool
This translation tool is not
functioning.
I got the first, it was not functioning.
I got the second, it was not
functioning.
And
And the third was not functioning.
The fourth
Third one.
And it took the fourth one to remember
that I take refuge before I plugged in
the ear
plugs.
And it was not functioning.
And then suddenly somebody came up and
helped me. We changed the channel, and
it was working for a time, but now it's
not functioning anymore.
And for sure, now I'm
thinking about the scientific reasons.
Okay.
And now it's getting complicated because
I took refuge, and the translation tool
was not working. So, now I'm missing the
trust in the refuge. How can I take
refuge if somebody's shooting a gun at
me? Uh yeah.
If it's not working with the translation
tool. Okay, good. Uh
I asked my lama this question.
He was very tough guy.
Those of you who knew him,
uh
he was a very tough guy, and he said
he looked at me, you know, and I said,
"I'm trying all this stuff, it doesn't
not working right now." He said, "Well,
you just go back to the old way then."
You know,
work as hard as you can,
you know, take vitamins,
you know,
uh
and then samsara will remind you that
there may be another way.
Okay? Because it will fail.
It will fail again and again and again.
You know, if you're not ready to jump,
okay, stay the old way.
You know, when you want money, just work
harder.
Uh when you want health, take more
vitamins, do more yoga.
Uh if you want a nice relationship,
you know,
steal the nicest handsomest boy or most
beautiful girl you can find from someone
else, okay? Go back to the old way
and try that for a while.
And when the disaster is big enough,
come back.
You know, okay? So, if that's he told me
that he he's very impatient sort of
lama. He's like, "Okay, then go back to
your old life.
No problem, you know?
When the pain is big enough, come back
to me."
Okay? So, I would say that. I'll say
that. Yeah.
Samsara will remind you that it doesn't
work.
Okay. We had one more promise of a
question. Who was that?
Vivian? Okay, that's the last one. Then
we have to do the
boundary.
Um
thank you, Geshe la. Your teaching
You're welcome. Gunga chee. Okay. Can I
have two questions? One she
But you only paid for one.
Okay.
So, Geshe la, the first question is you
taught us to offer anything we eat to
our teacher first before we eat them.
Last time in Thailand. And then now you
have given us a few more graces to do
before
eating anything. So,
what do I do? Do I put the teacher
offering first and do any one of this,
or what's the order Yeah, okay, good.
All of them are to your teacher. In the
end, all of them are to your teacher.
All six of them are to your teacher,
okay?
All All six of them are to your teacher.
So, don't worry about it. Uh
By the way, there's another tantric one
you want to know? Yeah. Uh
Don't offer it before you eat it.
Eat it first.
Like if you have a yogurt,
don't offer it. Just ah
Then swallow.
Then imagine it goes down
to the lama in the heart, and they're
like
That's a old custom. That's called the
body mandala.
There's an old teaching like that. So,
just imagine
it's coming down your throat, and
they're like they are like
And then take a bite, you know? So,
you can always do that.
Do the other grace first,
then eat, and then lama gets it anyway.
Okay? Second question.
Uh Geshe
get you that you taught the meditation
of exchanging self and others in level
eight and then at the end of that
meditation we should give away the
golden light ball in our heart to all
the people around us the people on the
street and to the
all the people in the city and even to
the all lives in the universe. So my
question is when I do this golden light
giving
should I just do it in a way like it's a
concept it's not that
real or should I just try to see every
real life
around me and try to give them the real
golden light.
You can't cover all the living beings in
your mind you know right now.
So you have to do blanket golden light.
You know just send it out
and
it's traveling right it's going out in
all directions.
Like send it out let it go for a while
let it go to
Shenzhen
then I don't know Europe
and it reaches New York and then you can
let it go and say please keep going I'll
check on you later.
You know like
you don't have to watch it go to
everywhere because it you'll never
finish the meditation okay. So you would
start it
and then you let it go but you don't
think it stopped you think it's still
traveling okay and when we do the fire
offering on
Thursday night it's the same thing the
smoke from the fire touches the top of
the sky
and some of it actually released into
the
outer space and it joins cosmic dust
and sooner or later it reaches every
star every planet. Then you don't have
to see it you just imagine logically
that dust will reach every planet of
this fire of this fire offering and and
so
later you'll be able to follow it all
the way with your mind after you become
Buddha but right now
you just
start it and then you let it go but you
imagine that it's still going okay.
All right good question I like your
questions.
Take a 15 minute break pee pee relax and
we'll go close the boundary.
Yes.
Let's do a Sashi bookie Scott you want
to do one?
Okay.
Two kinds of people
one doesn't work hard enough in retreat
the other one works too hard in retreat.
What's the percentage? 99%
try to work too hard in retreat they get
nervous they don't have a good time they
decide they're a bad person
they feel upset they don't relax okay.
This three day retreat is also meant
to give you a break
from your normal life. You are too busy
every one of us is too busy okay. Don't
bring that busy into retreat.
Okay leave it.
Okay if you have to start your yoga half
an hour late okay.
If you want to eat cookies instead of
yoga it's okay.
Okay
have some fun
and get some rest everybody needs a rest
your life is like a train high speed
Chinese train.
You know just take a break okay relax
enjoy Diamond Mountain enjoy your cabin
enjoy your friends.
Don't make the mistake to bring your
busy life into that cabin okay make it a
time of rest
relaxation
renewal
you know give yourself a break from your
life okay.
And if you can't do 28 meditations do
two.
Okay
and you're still a good person okay. If
you came here you're a good person okay
so don't please don't get all anxious
I didn't see Buddha on the second day of
retreat I'm a bad person you know just
relax you know when you relax
have a good time eat well rest well
meditate well
then then you have breakthrough you
don't get breakthrough by pushing
yourself you okay by getting nervous
okay just relax
okay and and stuff will come all right
so don't please don't get nervous or
anxious or
I'm not a good person or like that okay.
The goal is to be relaxed have a good
time
you know don't use your no one's going
to text you.
Okay this is your private
time to
to take a break from your life okay and
Diamond Mountain is always here for you
to come all year.
These cabins they don't go to Tucson
when you when you're not here they're
still here. The staff is still here.
It it's a place for you to come and rest
anytime you don't have to have a retreat
okay you don't have to have Lamrim
teaching you can come anytime okay call
Melissa write Melissa.
Is my cottage free? Yes.
Can I come next week for a break? Yes.
You know I just had a trouble with my
husband or I just lost my job or you
know
I don't feel so good okay so come
for a week take a break there doesn't
have to be Geshe Michael there.
Okay you there doesn't have to be
Tibetan grammar book
you know come and take a break this is
your place
we built it for you
and come in
let it be the place where you take a
break okay and it doesn't have to be a
special program just just come just let
Melissa know Michael and come okay.
It's here all the time.
All right.
Good luck.